Hi, today I wanted to talk about the radial basis functions and the way it was used and
implemented inside of the verb and adverb paper and I've done it in a separate video
because the mathematic behind the way they've used it and how they computed it is quite
complex and I don't want to make the video about the paper itself too long so this one
we just talk about the radial basis functions in the approximations and blending sense of
the paper and nothing else.
The first thing I would do is import all the libraries I would need and then what the paper
does is that they say that they have a bunch of adverbs and basically an adverb is a style
or anything in that way inside of an animation, so it could be the mood, the style, or turning left,
leaning right, all that kind of stuff. So all of that is adverbs for which you can try to blend
between different values. And then all those adverbs would drive all the degrees of freedom.
So for them, it would be the rotations and the translations of every bone. So the elbow,
the one degrees of freedom, the two degrees of freedoms of the wrist and all that kind of stuff.
I would make this a little more simple in this video so I can actually visualize what I'm doing.
So what I would do is that I will have the adverbs will just be left, right, top, bottom
inside of a two-degree and my degrees of freedom would just be a color. So I will have three degrees
of freedom, red, green, blue. So I have multi-dimensional inputs, multi-dimensional outputs
as the paper, but something that can visualize. So what we have is a bunch of points on the grid
and for each of those points I will have the corresponding color. So what I have is this
bunch of points on the grid and color for each point. And what I want to do is to be able to
basically interpolate those values and are having the color displayed along the entire square.
To make things a bit more interesting, instead of just doing basically two adverbs that are
really what they are, it's left right and top bottom, I'll turn them into four different adverbs,
all just positive, so I will have the right, the left, the top and the bottom as separate adverbs
instead of just negative and positive. It will answer, it will give you the exact same interpretations,
exact same values either way. It's just that in this case I have higher dimensional inputs,
which will be interesting to see that you're not stuck to 2Ds or anything. So I will turn those
coordinates into adverbs and those adverbs now are four-dimensional, so each points now,
so you get left, zero left of course, right 0.7 top and bottom for each point
and so I get a four-dimensional adverb space
and what they would try to do is basically allow you to interpolate those values
I've rewritten the mathematics as the way they use it except that I will use the names of what
I'm representing and not the degrees of freedom or that kind of stuff so basically what I have is
an interpolated color which is why I have the little c here because it's one degree
of freedom inside of the color so c would be red green or blue so the interpreted value of one
specific point and remember that point is inside of the ad-web space so left right top bottom
So, it's a 4D point.
It would be the sum of the radial coefficients multiplied by the radial basis functions.
The same way we're doing radial basis functions usually.
So, it's the radial basis functions for a specific point, multiply for the weights,
And then, see, because I'm multi-dimensional now, I have a weight per example, the little
I, and per color.
So I will have, in my case, I have seven points, and I get three colors, so I get 21 different
weights in this case.
And on top of that, you add a linear approximations of the, of the interpretations.
And the way you're doing it this is now it's per adverbs, what you will have is a coefficient,
a linear coefficient per color, per adverbs, and it goes through the linear functions instead
of the radial basis one.
This is fairly similar to the way we were doing in radial basis functions where we had
a polynomial constraint.
added a bunch of a bunch of constraints and to do this we we build the matrix when you remember we
had one and then x squared x cube and so on depending on the degrees of freedom of your
polynomial here will be the same what you try to do is to find for all the points in our 40 space
we try to find an hyperplane that will best approximates all those points. So that's what
this tries to do, tries to find an hyperplane that goes through all the points and approximates
as best as you can do. It's basically a linear regression. And to do this we would do the same
kind of system that what we did in the radial basis functions. I will actually put a 1 and then
instead of doing x x square and so on i will basically do one and then adverb one
adverb two adverb three adverb four i get four dimensions so it's one left right top bottom
so and i do this for every points i will have and that gives me a big matrix with a bunch of ones
all the values for the all those values here for the left all those values here for the right
and so on and so on. And then I can try to solve for the actual coefficients.
Except that, of course, you don't have a real answer. I cannot just do inverse matrix and solve
as we did when we were doing the radial basis functions. Now what I have to do is to go through
a least square to find the best approximations. So this is exactly what I would do here. What I have
is the advert matrix. What I do is that I compute the ones and then all my adverbs and then after
that I do a linear least square so I can find the best solutions and that gives me these coefficients
and it gives me the coefficients for all my degrees of freedom so all my colors at once. So
basically what I have is the the red the green and the blue so one for each values
and I get the five different coefficients and the five coefficients is the coefficients for
the one and then for left top left right top bottom so I get five and I get three values here
The idea behind this is I could have solved for one color at a time, I could have solved
only for the red, then the green, then the blue. It would have given me the same answer,
it's just that I can compute the multidimensional in one go inside of NumPy.
So that's how all my linear interpolations is working. Now what I would have is I can
display the interpolated linear approximations so what I do is I make a big grid of 40 points and
40 points I get 1600 points for which I have all the coordinates and I would turn that into my
adverb space because I'm not interested in coordinates again I'm still interested in
blending different adverbs together so I turned that into my four-dimensional adverbs
And then I create the interpolations at the data the same way.
And then I can just multiply my matrix together and that gives me the color.
So what I would have is this.
So the linear approximations give me this.
It's the best color I can find with linear approximations.
So that's what you have here.
Now what we want to do is to get something a little better
that just that linear approximations what we have what we want is to be able to get the exact
values here and that's why now we need to use the radial basis functions on top of what we've done
and the way we would do this is we would compute the residual say the amount of error the linear
approximation is giving for each point and so we take the real values I have and I will
subtract the linear approximations and that gives me the residual so the amount of error the
linear approximations gave me and so this is the residual it gives me for every point
so my seven points and for the red the green and the blue again.
And now that's the residual values that we will go and plug inside of the radial basis functions.
If you remember what we did the radial basis functions, what we had is a kernel that turns
any distance into values that goes between some parameters, some values depending of the type of
kernel you want to use and we had to use the Gaussian kernel. What they used inside of this
paper is the delayed cubic B spline. The cubic B spline curve is something we've already seen
when we were watching the doing the videos for the cubic B spline and it's the same formula.
So I will use alpha of that b-spline, cubic b-spline as these functions and I can display
what it looks like if you remember. So it's split into two functions that stick together.
And the advantage of the cubic b-spline like this is that it has a radius of two
and anything that is further away than two is just zero.
So you got a nice curve and then at two,
every further than two, everything at zero.
So now that's the kernel they would use.
So what they could do is that basically say,
as I said, you get all that,
if you remember how to solve
for the radial basis functions,
We build that big matrix with a distance
between each point and each points.
And then we multiply that with the weights
and equal our values.
And we solve for that system to find all those weights.
Except that what we have here is that we don't solve
for the values itself, we solve for the residual.
So the amount of error, the approximations,
the linear approximations are gave us.
And then the distance is where it's a bit different than the radial basis functions where we were
just giving the Gaussian kernel and the same distance, the same way of computing a distance
for each of them. What they said, they said that the D is built this way. And what it means,
it's actually, it just means that it goes through the Bayesier, the cubic Bayesier,
but what you feed inside of the cubic Bezier is the distance of the points, so
that's R, I1 is the distance between your points and the example divided by
an alpha and what the alpha represents it's basically the distance of all the
the closest point. So what they really want to do is to make sure that they will only do
radial basis functions with all the values that fairly close to the points we have and anything
that is too far away inside of our approximations is not used. And basically to do this, what I said
is that for every point, you check all the points, all the other points when you build that matrix.
you compute the distance for all the different points and then you take the closest distance
and then you divide all the points all the distance you divide by that one which means
that basically what you have is that the closest point has a distance of one and then everything
else will be a bit further away and everything that is actually at a distance of two or more
has no influence so it means that you only have values that are fairly close to you that are used
inside the radial business functions and everything that is further away is discarded and not used
so you don't have weird interpretations of posts that really far from each other
influencing each other so what they have here in this case is really that everything that's close
has an influence, everything further away has no influence. So again, I will compute the distance
as we did earlier, except that this time it's a 4D Euler distance. So I compute the distance
between every point and every point and I give me this matrix again with diagonals all the zeros
because points with itself is the distance of zeros. And then I can compute those alphas
for each point basically what I do is that I go through every row and I try
to find the minimal values I have inside of that row which is not zero and that
will give me the alpha by which I need to divide all those values for each
column basically to give me the proper values scaled and now that I have the
alpha I can take the distance and I can divide those distance by the alpha. And basically what it gives
you now is a matrix where you know the zeros are still zeros and then the smallest values I had
is became one and everything is bigger than one so it gets zero one and then something a little
bigger than one so all of those have influence and I know that everything that is pass two will
have zero influence in my radial basis functions. So not all those will have
influence but this one has the most influence and then everything else a
bit less and everything that reach 2 has no influence. So I get a bunch of
values that will be discarded when we will be computing the radial
basis functions. Now that I have those scaled distance I can make them go
through the kernel itself. That gives me now this distance now for all my different coefficients.
And again, exactly the same way we did in the radial basis functions. Now I have my matrix of
distances. I get my matrix of values. I can solve to get the coefficients. And I get the
the coefficients now here for my seven points and again I'm computing every
degrees of freedom at once in those matrices so I get the values for all the
reds the green and the blues at once and I can easily display now the final
results it's basically as the functions were doing on the top is you add the
linear interpolations you did and then you add the radial basis functions
together and when you do this you get this interpolations and now you can see
that we have something fairly neat when my inputs are not that visible anymore so
all of that has been properly interpolated. Now it's tricky to understand
And why it was done this way, basically the advantage of doing it this way is that the
linear approximations give you an opportunity to do extrapolations.
If you do, if you remember, radial basis functions are really bad at extrapolating.
But the linear interpolations is just, it's fairly bad anyway, but it can give you extrapolations.
So the linear approximation silos you to have extrapolations.
And then the radial basis functions
is only looking at poses that are fairly close to the examples.
So it's avoiding having influences from posts
that far away when you have really scattered data.
So that's the reason why they've split it into,
you have an approximations that is not too bad
when there is no data and that can give you extrapolations.
and then the interpolations when you have data,
which is fairly good.
What I will do now is just for the paper itself.
So I would turn all the code I have here into a big class
so I can reuse and recall.
And basically it's just all the functions we had.
I get my base here that is defined here.
I get the initializations where you will give
all your points and adverbs as inputs
when you init the radial basis functions
and I would pre-compute everything
that can be pre-computed.
So the D for the distances, the linear adverbs, the alphas,
all of that is stored and saved.
And then you can fit your data
through that radial basis functions.
So basically is the step when you actually compute
the coefficients, the real coefficients you want to use.
So you can fit and it will return the linear coefficients
for your data and the radial coefficients for your data.
And then you can call the radial basic functions
to do the interpolations.
And then what you do is that you give him
the linear coefficients you had received,
the radial coefficients you had received,
and the points or the points you want to interpolate
to get the interpolations.
While I split it in two different functions like this one,
it's basically, even if all my adverbs are defined
advance because I would know what the adverbs I want to use. I can fit different type of curves.
I can fit all my degrees of freedom or I can fit only one or depending on how I want to use these
functions I can reuse the same adverbs with different input data and that will be useful for
the paper so that's why I split it into this way. Now we can see that it actually works.
So if I do the color again, just doing the RBF, giving the adverbs, then I fit
my data and then I try to interpolate with all the data points
interpolations and then that's it. You have it. All that code now has just
three lines here and it works with any dimensions. So in this case have four
dimensions adverbs and three degrees of freedom. I can do it in 1D as we were
doing before, so I get one-dimensional input, one-dimensional output, and that's
the interpolation they will give me. See, it's not perfect if I was doing a
pure radial basis function they would give me a better answer than this one,
but in this you could see that it did the linear interpolations as best as it
could and then it did the interpretation in between. So that's the
implementations of the radial basis part of the paper. I'll see you in the actual
paper analysis to see how this is used and how it can be used to blend
animations together and how it was done. See you in the next video.